Guide to the Kip Lornell and Charles Stephenson Washington Go-Go collection, 1978-2008 MS2177
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Kip Lornell and Charles Stephenson Washington Go-Go collection
1978-2008
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lornell, Kip
Stephenson, Charles C.
MS2177
4 Linear Feet
Collection contains correspondence, promotional materials, clippings, interviews, photographs, slides, audio cassette tapes, electronic records, and other materials. The material dates from 1978-2008, and was collected by Kip Lornell and Charles Stephenson in the course of their research on go-go music. The materials document the evolution of go-go and the cultural and political role of go-go in Washington, D.C. Go-go originated in Washington, D.C. in the 1970s. It is a subgenre of funk, and is characterized by continuous complex rhythm arrangements and crowd call and response. The term "go-go" refers both to the style of music and the venue in which music is performed.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Kip Lornell and Charles Stephenson in 2002. A second donation by Kip Lornell came to the library in 2014.
Historical or Biographical Note
Christopher "Kip" Lornell (b. 1953) and Charles Stephenson are the authors of the book "The Beat: Go-Go's Fusion of Funk and Hip-Hop." Lornell is a noted ethnomusicologist, and a professor in The George Washington University's Department of Music. He received his Bachelor of Science in Cultural Sciences in 1975 from State University of New York Empire State College, his Master of Arts in Folklore in 1976 from University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, and his Ph. D. in Ethnomusicology (Regional American Music) in 1983 from University of Memphis. Stephenson is a cultural and political activist in Washington, D.C., and a strong advocate for go-go music. He was the manager of the influential go-go group Experience Unlimited. He works as an associate in the management consulting firm of Dellums & Associates.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, promotional materials, clippings, interviews, photographs, slides, audio cassette tapes, electronic records, and other materials. The material dates from 1978-2008, and was collected by Kip Lornell and Charles Stephenson in the course of their research on go-go music. The materials document the evolution of go-go and the cultural and political role of go-go in Washington, D.C. Go-go originated in Washington, D.C. in the 1970s. It is a subgenre of funk, and is characterized by continuous complex rhythm arrangements and crowd call and response. The term "go-go" refers both to the style of music and the venue in which music is performed. In the 1980's, go-go became associated with drugs and violence, and many go-go clubs were closed in Washington, D.C.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Papers, Images, Audiocassettes, Electronic records and 2014 donation.
Washington (D.C.); Musicians; Color slides; Music; Audiocassettes; Go-go (music); Performances; Photographs; Lornell, Kip; Stephenson, Charles C.
- Papers, 1978-2002; MS2177 Series 1; 1 Linear foot
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, promotional materials, clippings, interviews, and other materials. The material dates from 1978-2002. The documents contain information about go-go music, performers, and venues, as well as the media perception of go-go. Of particular interest is a transcript of a conference held in 2000, entitled "Gimme That Beat! Twenty-five Years of Go-Go," at which both Lornell and Stephenson spoke. The series also contains interviews with go-go musicians, flyers and promotional materials from go-go shows, go-go magazines, and documents related to the effort to disassociate go-go from violence.
  - C.J.'s Uptown Crew, 1986-1989 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1984-2001 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
  - Committee to Save Go-Go, 1986-1996 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Community, 1998-2000 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Street Awards, 1989 (Box 1A, Folder 5)
  - Folk Arts Program--D.C. Commission on the Arts, 1990 (Box 1A, Folder 6)
  - Flyers and promotional materials, 1978-2000 (Box 1A, Folder 7)
  - General articles, 1986-1999 (Box 1A, Folder 8)
  - "Gimme That Beat! Twenty-five Years of Go-Go" Conference transcript [1/2], 2000 (Box 1A, Folder 9)
  - "Gimme That Beat! Twenty-five Years of Go-Go" Conference transcript [2/2], 2000 (Box 1A, Folder 10)
  - Go-Go Drugs Free, 1986-1987 (Box 1A, Folder 11)
  - Go-Go on film, 1985-2001 (Box 1A, Folder 12)
  - Go-Go outside of D.C., 1984-2000 (Box 1A, Folder 13)
  - Humanities Council of Washington, D.C. Grant, 1999-2000 (Box 1B, Folder 1)
  - Interviews, 1988-1998 (Box 1B, Folder 2)
  - Legal matters, 1984-1991 (Box 1B, Folder 3)
  - Magazines, 1997-1999 (Box 1B, Folder 4)
  - Mob TV and videos, 1994-2000 (Box 1B, Folder 5)
  - Musicians, 1979-2000 (Box 1B, Folder 6)
  - 900 Go Go, 1990 (Box 1B, Folder 7)
  - Release forms, 1998-2000 (Box 1B, Folder 8)
  - Research--notes, drafts, 1985-2000 (Box 1B, Folder 9)
  - Venues, 1988-2000 (Box 1B, Folder 10)
  - Web sites, 1998-2002 (Box 1B, Folder 11)
- Images, 1985 ca - 2000 ca; MS2177 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains color photographs, black-and-white photographs, and color slides of go-go performers, shows, and events. The images are undated and most are unidentified.
  - Photographs (Box 1B, Folder 12)
  - Photographs (Box 1B, Folder 13)
  - Photographs (Box 1B, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (Box 1C, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1C, Folder 2)
  - Color slides (Box 1C, Folder 3)
- Audiocassettes, 1998-2001; MS2177 Series 3; 1 Linear foot
  This series consists of audiocassette tapes dating from 1998 to 2001. The cassettes contain interviews with musicians, filmmakers, and other prominent figures in the world of go-go music; a recording of a conference on the subject of go-go; and recordings of go-go shows.
  - Charlie Fenwick, 03/10/1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Moe Shorter, 03/17/1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ken Moore, 03/31/1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Mack, 10/06/1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Funk, Stephenson / Lornell, Darnell and Andre, 10/27/1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Funk, Kip, Charles / Darnell, Andre (Rare Essence), 10/28/1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Benny Harley, 01/22/1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Kato, 02/17/1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Legends Feat. Lil Benny / Legend Nite Club, 04/23/1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rene Dickerson / Funky "D", 11/03/1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Go Go Conference #1, 04/15/2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Go Go Conference #2, 04/15/2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Go Go Conference #3, 04/15/2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bruce Brown / Tom Goldfogle, 08/01/2000-08/04/2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Gregory "Sugar Bear" Elliott, 09/11/2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Max Kidd, 10/07/2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Andre Lucas / Lonnie Johnson Self Esteem, 10/11/2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Borders Books Go Go Talk, 07/07/2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Borders Books Go Go Talk, 09/07/2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Andre Lucas (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Goldfogle and Brown back-up (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Dare by Michael A. Davenport (Kidd) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified audiocassette (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Electronic records, 1998-2000; MS2177 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series consists of floppy disks dating from 1998 to 2000. The disks consist of word processing files in various formats containing transcripts of interviews with musicians and prominent figures in the world of go-go music.
  - Charlie Fenwick, 03/10/1998 (Box 1C, Folder 4)
  - Charlie Fenwick interview, 03/10/1998 (Box 1C, Folder 5)
  - Moe Shorter, 03/17/1998 (Box 1C, Folder 6)
  - Ken Moore, 03/31/1997 (Box 1C, Folder 7)
  - Interview transcriptions, 1999 (Box 1C, Folder 8)
  - Lornell/Go-go--Mrs. Mack interview, 1999 (Box 1C, Folder 9)
  - Gogo interview--Rene Dickerson and Funky D, 2000 (Box 1C, Folder 10)
  - Goldfogle t Brown, 2000 (Box 1C, Folder 11)
- 2014 donation, 1984-2003; Series 5; 2 Linear Feet 2 document boxes, 1 slim document box and 1 flat box
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Paper records and Cassettes, VHS, and CDs
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains publicity materials both from clubs and from media outlets, programs, correspondence, VHS, audiocassettes and cds of musical acts. The records are an addition to the previous donation and cover the same topics. These records date from 1982-2008.
  - Papers, 1984-2003; Series 5 Subseries 1
    Arranged in no particular order.
    This subseries contains articles, magazines, publicity, programs and correspondence related to the Go-Go music scene in Washington DC. The material dates from 1984-2003.
    - C.J.'s Uptown Crew, 1984; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Publicity, 1986-2002; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper articles, 1990-2002; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Go-Go Music Project, Inc, 1989-2002; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - WAMA X-town / Showcase, 1991; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Portfolio for assessment of prior experiential learning by Mary Carlson and Charles Stephenson, 1991; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Murder Dog Magazine Vol. 9, no. 1, 2002; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Go-Go stuff, 2002; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - GoGoBeat.com, 2002-2003; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The Go-Go movie, 2003; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - To teach the beat, 2012 March 23; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Optimystic Tribe, Undated; Series 5 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Cassettes, VHS and CDs, 1982-2008; Series 5 Subseries 2
    This subseries contains cassettes, VHS tapes, and CDs of Go Go musicians both albums and recordings of events. These date from 1982-2008.
    - CJ's Uptown Crew "Live", undated; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 1)
    - CJ's Uptown Crew Live & CJ's Uptown Crew Live Cornucopia TV show, undated; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 2)
    - CJ's Uptown Crew Live and CJ's Uptown Crew Live, undated; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 11)
    - E.U. Captial Centre, 1982 September 5; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 3)
    - E.U. Apollo, 1988 April 23; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 9)
    - Icycle Metroworld Showcase Northeast Grooves, undated; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 4)
    - BET Tonight #981020 Foreman vs. Jimmy Ellis, 1998 October 17; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 5)
    - Rockin' DC 9 min. Demo, undated; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 6)
    - Go Go Swing final cut, undated; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 7)
    - Go Go PA Tape, 1990 November 1; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 8)
    - Go Go on MHZ, undated; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 10)
    - A Capital Beat, 2002; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 12)
    - Straight UP Go Go, 1992 March 25; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Videocassette 13)
    - CJ's Sat Jam & [unreadable word], 2000 August 26; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cassette 1)
    - D.E.T.T. and T.T.E.D Super Fun Set, 1984; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cassette 2)
    - Trouble Funk P.A. Classics Vol. 1, 1992; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cassette 3)
    - Trouble Funk Hard to Beat, 1989; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cassette 4)
    - Go Go Live At the Capital Centre, 1987; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cassette 5)
    - Hard to Beat Go Go Vol. 1, 1989; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cassette 6)
    - Mass Extension Can You Feel It? Stay with Me, 1991; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cassette 7)
    - Rare Essense Doin It Old School Style, 2001; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 1)
    - EU Cold Kickin It, 1990; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 2)
    - Chuck Brown Your Game... Live at the 9:30 Club, 2001; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 3)
    - Eva Cassidy Imagine, 2002; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 4)
    - Yasmeen Walking in the way of love, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 5)
    - Go Go Live at Witmer Park, 1992; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 6)
    - The Beulah Baptist Church Choir and Jas Funk, 2008; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 7)
    - Rare Essence We go on and on, 1994; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 8)
    - Rare Essence Re-2000, 1999; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 9)
    - The Beat Go Go's Fusion of Funk and Hip Hop, 2001; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 10)
    - Mass Extension Can you Feel It? Stay With me, 1991; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 11)
    - Lissen Can you Hear Us Now?, 2007; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 12)
    - Chuck Brown We Got This, 2010 (Box 6, Cd 13)
    - E.U. $ Make Money $, 1996; Series 5 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Cd 14)